Jacobo Sedelmayr letters and reports, 1744-1751
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Jacobo Sedelmayr letters and reports, 1744-1751
AZ 437
Sedelmayr, Jacobo, 1703-1779
Letters and reports, from Sedelmayr to Christóbal de Escobar y Llamas, Juan Antonio Balthassar, Philipp Segesser, and Andrés Xavier García, relating to conditions in Pimeria Alta at the missions and surrounding areas. Includes reports on explorations to the Gila and Colorado Rivers which describe the terrain and customs of the people encountered.
.4 linear feet
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
None.
Biographical Note
Jacobo Sedelmayr was born in Freising, Bavaria, on January 12, 1703. A Jesuit missionary, he was sent to New Spain in 1736 and was assigned to the Pimeria Alta region, at the mission at Tubutama. This region, the northernmost frontier of New Spain, now includes Arizona and the Mexican states of Sonora and Sinaloa. It was the northernmost frontier of New Spain. Here he worked to convert the native people to Christianity, to build churches, and to improve living conditions. He also undertook several expeditions to investigate lands and people to the north.
In 1751, eight missions were active in Pimeria Alta. Sedelmayr was Visitador Provincial, located at Tubutama. Also that year, a revolt of the Pimas created a major setback for the Jesuits. Sometime between 1754 and 1762, Sedelmayr was transferred to the mission of Tecoripa, in the province of Sonora. In 1764, he became professor at the College of Matape on the Yaqui River. On June 25, 1767, the Jesuits were expelled from Mexico. Sedelmayr found refuge in Spain and died at Aldea de Avila, Spain on February 12, 1779.
Organization
This collection is organized into two series
Series I: Holograph Letters and Report, 1744-1751
Series II: Photocopies, from John Galvin, Collector, of Letters and Reports, 1745-1751
Scope and Content Note
Letters and reports, from Sedelmayr to various Jesuit leaders, describe conditions in Pimeria Alta at the missions and surrounding areas, discuss administrative concerns, and report on explorations along the Gila and Colorado Rivers.
The documents provide a detailed account of the land and people he encountered including Pima, Tohono O'odham, Apache, Yuman, and Seri. They also contain information on the organization and operations of the Jesuit missions in the Pimeria Alta. Correspondents are Christobal de Escobar y Llamas, Juan Antonio Balthassar, Philipp Segesser, and Andres Xavier Garcia.
Three letters and one report are contemporary holograph documents. Seven letters and two reports are photocopies of holograph documents. All are in Spanish, with some lapses into German interspersed; and are accompanied by typescript English translations or summaries.
Access Terms
Sedelmayr, Jacobo, 1703-1779
Balthassar, Juan Antonio, 1697-1763
García, Andrés Xavier
Escobar y Llamas, Christóbal de, d. 1760
Segesser, Philipp, 1689-1761
Jesuits -- Missions -- Southwest, New -- History -- Sources
Missionaries -- New Spain -- History -- Sources
Explorers -- New Spain -- History -- Sources
Pimeria Alta (Mexico and Ariz.) -- Church history -- Sources
Southwest, New -- Discovery and exploration -- Sources
Correspondence
Reports
Container List
- Series I: Holograph Letters and Report, 1744-1751
  - Letter to Father Provincial Cristobal de Escobar y Llamas, from the Mission of Tubutama, Pimeria Alta. December 31,1744 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Holograph in Spanish and Latin describing his travels in southwest Arizona and along the Gila River in October and November 1743. Includes extensive description of people encountered in the region.
  - Report of an exploration, written at Tubutama, and copied by Fr. Bartholome Saenz at Caborca. November 16,1748 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Holograph in Spanish of a 1748 exploration along the Gila River to its confluence with the Colorado River. Extensive description of the geography and the people encountered.
  - Letter to Juan Antonio Balthassar, S.J., from Tubutama. April 1,1749 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Holograph, in Spanish and German. Concerns affairs at the mission, including accounts of trips in the area, relationships with Yuma, Seri, Apache people, and proposals for further missionary work.
  - Letter to Philipp Segesser, S.J., from Tubutama. January 8,1751 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Holograph, in Spanish, relates chiefly to his opposition to the sending of missionaries to certain pueblos in Pimeria Alta. An additional note refers to proposed activities in California.
- Series II: Photocopies, from John Galvin, Collector, of Letters and Reports, 1745-1751
  - Letter to Christobal de Escobar y Llamas, from Tubutama. May 29,1745 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Describes his exploration of the Gila and Colorado Rivers, his encounters with the Cocomaricopas, and his mission work in Pimeria Alta.
  - Letter to Juan Antonio Balthassar, from Tubutama. March 22,1747 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Gives information about Franciscan missionary work with the Navajo, and his own work in Pimeria Alta. Includes material about the presidios of Terrenate, San Xavier del Bac, Quevavi, and Fronteras.
  - Letter to Andres Xavier Garcia, from Tubutama. June 15,1748 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Reports on the missions and missionaries in the Pimeria Alta region.
  - Letter with no addressee, from Tubutama. November 16,1748 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Summary of his journey to native villages on the Gila and Colorado Rivers. Describes the Yumas and their land.
  - Report of his explorations of the Colorado and Gila Rivers. November-December 1750 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Describes conditions and makes recommendations for locations of missions.
  - Letter to Father Provincial Juan Antonio Balthassar, from Tubutama. January 9,1751 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Discusses his 1750 explorations, his mission plans, and his work on a History of Pimeria Alta. He suggests measures for the protection of the missions.
  - Letter to Father Provincial Juan Antonio Balthassar, from Tubutama. January 13,1751 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Relates events at San Miguel de Sonoytac and other news.
  - Report on his visitation of the missions of Pimeria Alta, from Tubutama. May 10,1751 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Describes conditions at Quevavi, San Xavier del Bac, Santa Maria Ssuanca, and San Ignacio, and makes recommendations for improvement.
  - Letter to Father Provincial Juan Antonio Balthassar, from Tubutama. May 21,1751 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Relates mission news, gives suggestions for assignment of missionaries, and discourages further exploration beyond the Colorado until natives have been pacified.